William N. Fenton Papers 1933-2000 Mss.Ms.Coll.20
American Philosophical Society
- Series IIb. Iroquois Documentary History Project, 1635-1989; 3 boxes; 1.5 linear feet
  - Journal of Griffith Evans, 1784-1785--Photocopy from Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, 1941 (Box Series IIb-1)
  - "Journal of Samuel Maclay, While Surveying the West Branch of the Susquehanna, the Sinnemahoning and the Allegheny Rivers, in 1790"--Photocopy, 1887 (Box Series IIb-1)
  - La Barre, Governor. Humiliation by an Ondondaga Orator at Hungry Bay, 5 Sep. 1684 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - "The Law Governing the Behavior of Federal Chiefs"--Collected by J.N.B. Hewitt from John A. Gibson, John Buck, Sr., and Abram Charles, 1917-1937 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - "Law of the Woman Chief"--Collected by J.N.B. Hewitt from Abram Charles, 1923, 1928 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - "The Law of the Woman Chief"--Collected by J.N.B. Hewitt from John A. Gibson, n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Maps in Public Archives of Canada, Ottawa, n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Marie de l'Incarnation. Correspondence, 1681 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Meriam, Eben. Letters to--In American Philosophical Society Library, 1853-1854 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box Series IIb-2)
    - Folder #1, 1932-1959, n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
    - Folder #2, n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Montbas, Le Vicomte de. Avec Lafayette Chez les Iroquois, 1929 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Montreal and Quebec. Grand Settlement at, 1701 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - New York Colonial Manuscripts, 1770s (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Newberry Library Research Trip, 13-20 Feb. 1989 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Nottaway Vocabulary Collected by John Wood (in American Philosophical Society Library), 1800 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Oswego, Retreat from. Extract from the Votes of the Assembly of New-York, 1744 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - "Pennsylvania Material in the Buffalo Historical Society", n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Provincial Council. Minutes of the (Box Series IIb-2)
    - Folder #1, 1743-1752 (Box Series IIb-2)
    - Folder #2, 1753-1756 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Radisson, Pierre Esprit, n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
  - "The Seneca Tradition of League", n.d. (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Society for the Propagation of the Gospel. From the Archives of the, 1954 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Tootle, James Roger. "Anglo-Indian Relations in the Northern Theatre of the French and Indian War, 1748-1761"--Notes, 1972 (Box Series IIb-2)
  - Treaties (Box Series IIb-3)
    - Folder #1, 1655-1682 (Box Series IIb-3)
    - Folder #2, 1686-1694 (Box Series IIb-3)
    - Folder #3, 1696-1745 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Treaties (France), 1666 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Treaty Between Benjamin Fletcher and the Five Nations, 1694 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - "The Treaty Held with the Indians of the Six Nations at Philadelphia, July, 1742" -- From The American Magazine (Box Series IIb-3)
  - "Treaty Wampum Belts"--Collected by J.N.B. Hewitt from John Buck, Sr., 1896 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Wallace, Anthony F.C. Iroquois Neutrality, 1701 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Wendell, Jacob. Papers--Massachusetts Delegate to Conference with Six Nations, 23 Jul. 1748 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Wolley, Charles. A Two Years Journal in New-York: And Part of Its Territories in America, 1701 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Wood, William. New England's Prospect, 1865 (Box Series IIb-3)
  - Zeisberger, David. Letters and Diaries--Transcripts, 1769-1770 (Box Series IIb-3)
- Series III. Works by Fenton, 1711-1991; 13 boxes; 6.25 linear feet
  Fenton's typewritten and handwritten drafts, and outlines, preparatory notes and research for articles, books, reviews, lectures, and tributes to colleagues. This series is arranged by title. Cross-references appear for correspondence, photographs, and reprints which appear in this series. The earliest materials in this series are research items gathered for The Customs of the American Indian Compared with the Customs of Primitive Times by Father Joseph François Lafitau, including photocopies of several journals from the early 1700s. Fenton's earliest manuscripts were written in 1931: "Outdoor Wisdom," a review of William Hillcourt's The Boy Campers, and "Thoreau on Education," a paper written when Fenton was a student at Dartmouth. There is also a 1932 paper, "The Connecticut Algonkians," which was written for George P. Murdock's course in ethnology at Yale. Of note are the drafts, notes, and research for The False Faces of the Iroquois. "Social and Ceremonial Organization of the Six Nations Reserve in 1910," a proposal for publication of Alexander A. Goldenweiser's notebooks, is interesting in the way Fenton chooses to organize the material. Also of note is Fenton's translation of the Deganawidah epic as it was conveyed to Goldenweiser. Several drafts of "Mohawk," co-authored by Elisabeth Tooker, appear in this series as well. Materials for several of Fenton's articles on Horatio Hale are filed under "Hale."
  - "'Aboriginally Yours,' Jesse J. Cornplanter, Hah-Yonh-Wonh-Ish, the Snipe, Seneca, 1889-1957"--Ms., 31 Mar. 1976 (Box Series III-1)
  - "The Adoption of WNF into the Hawk Clan, Coldspring Longhouse 26 Jan. 1934"--Ms., 24 Mar. 1986 (Box Series III-1)
  - "The Agricultural Tribes of the Northeast"--Ms. and notes, Dec. 1941 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Agriculture in the Northeast: An Interpretation" (Box Series III-1)
    -See Ser. III, "The Agricultural Tribes of the Northeast"
  - American Indian and White Relations to 1830: Needs and Opportunities for Study--Reviews, 1957-1958 (Box Series III-1)
  - "American Indian History and Historiography"--Lecture, 1974 (Box Series III-1)
  - "American Participation in VIIth International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, Moscow, August 3-10, 1964"--Draft, 9 Oct. 1964 (Box Series III-1)
  - "American Participation in VIIth International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, Moscow, August 3-10, 1964"--Ms., 12 Mar. 1965 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Answers to Governor Cass's Questions by Jacob Jameson, a Seneca (ca. 1821-1825)", 1969 (Box Series III-1)
    -See also Ser. I, Detroit Public Library
  - "An Anthropological Perspective on the Treaty-Making Process"--Outline, 4 Mar. 1980 (Box Series III-1)
  - Anthropology and the Public: The Role of Museums by H.H. Frese--Review, 1961 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Anthropology and the University"--Lecture, 8 May 1968, 1969 (Box Series III-1)
  - Area Studies in American Universities, [1948] (Box Series III-1)
  - "At the Wood's Edge"--Lecture, 14 Apr. 1985 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Captain Hide's Observations on the Five Nations of Indians at New-Yorke, 1698"--Edited by William N. Fenton, 17 Feb. 1964 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Cherokee and Iroquois Connections Revisited"--Ms., 1978 (Box Series III-1)
    -See also Ser. IIa, Cherokee-Iroquois Conference
  - "Collecting Materials for a Political History of the Six Nations"--Lecture, 5 Nov. 1948 (Box Series III-1)
  - The Colonial Records of South Carolina: Documents Relating to Indian Affairs, 1754-1765 by William L. McDowell, Jr.--Review, 1970 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Comment on an SOS of Ethnology"--Ms., 8 Sep. 1952 (Box Series III-1)
  - Comments on Certain Iroquois Masks by Joseph Keppler--Review, 1942 (Box Series III-1)
  - "Concerning the Longhouse," or "The League" (Box Series III-1)
    -See Ser. III, Deganawidah Epic
  - "The Condolence Council in Iroquois Politics"--Lecture, 14 May 1948 (Box Series III-1)
  - "The Connecticut Algonkians"--Ms., 1932 (Box Series III-1)
  - Council Fires on the Upper Ohio: A Narrative of Indian Affairs in the Upper Ohio Valley Until 1795 by Randolph C. Downes--Review, [12 Jan. 1941] (Box Series III-1)
  - Cultural Basis of Learning and Memory Systems Among Native Americans (Box Series III-1)
  - Customs of the American Indians Compared With the Customs of Primitive Times by Father Joseph François Lafitau (Box Series III-1)
    -See Ser. I, Condominas, Georges
    -See Ser. I, Cross, Michael
    -See Ser. I, Duchet, Michèle
    -See Ser. I, Lamalle, Edmond
    -See Ser. I, Moore, Elizabeth
    -See Ser. I, Pauliot, Léon
    -See Ser. I, Tissot, Georges
  - Customs of the American Indians Compared With the Customs of Primitive Times by Father Joseph François Lafitau--Notes and Research (Box Series III-1)
    -See also Ser. I, Haan, R.L.
    -See also Ser. I, Haugh, Georgia
    -See also Ser. I, Neill, D.G.
    -See also Ser. I, Wright, Gordan
    - Folder #1, 1711-1722, 1961-1974 (Box Series III-1)
    - Folder #2, 1722-1725, 1928, 1961 (Box Series III-1)
    - Folder #3, 1856-1933, 1962-1966 (Box Series III-1)
    - Folder #4, 1913-1963 (Box Series III-2)
    - Folder #5, 1960-1970 (Box Series III-2)
  - Customs of the American Indians Compared With the Customs of Primitive Times by Father Joseph François Lafitau--Publicity, 1974, 1977 (Box Series III-2)
  - Deganawidah Epic (Box Series III-2)
    - Folder #1 (pp.1-21), 1969 (Box Series III-2)
      Fenton's rendition of Floyd G. Lounsbury's translation of Alexander A. Goldenwiser's 1912 transcription
    - Folder #2 (pp.22-203), 1969-1971 (Box Series III-2)
      Floyd G. Lounsbury's translation of Alexander A. Goldenweiser's 1912 transcription
    - Folder #3 (pp.204-427), 1969-1971 (Box Series III-2)
    - Folder #4 (pp.428-525), 1943 (Box Series III-2)
      Fenton's and Simeon Gibson's translation of Alexander A. Goldenweiser's 1912 transcription
    - Folder #5, n.d. (Box Series III-2)
      Notes
    - Folder #6, n.d. (Box Series III-2)
      Fenton's complete version
    - Folder #7, n.d. (Box Series III-2)
    - Folder #8, n.d. (Box Series III-3)
  - "The Deganawidah Legend: A Tradition of the Founding of the Five Iroquois Tribes" by Chief John Arthur Gibson to J.N.B. Hewitt, 1899; translation completed and edited by Fenton with Simeon Gibson, 1941--Ms. (Draft version), 2 folders (Box Series III-3)
  - "The Deganawidah Legend: A Tradition of the Founding of the Five Iroquois Tribes" by Chief John Arthur Gibson to J.N.B. Hewitt, 1899; translation completed and edited by Fenton with Simeon Gibson, 1941--Ms. (Final version) (Box Series III-3)
  - "Ethnology and Historiography"--Ms., Dec. 1952 (Box Series III-3)
    -See also Ser. IIa, American Anthropological Assocation
  - "Factionalism in American Indian Society"--Ms., 1952 (Box Series III-3)
    -See also Ser. I, Hoebel, E. Adamson
  - The False Faces of the Iroquois (Draft)--Ms. (Box Series III-3)
    - Folder #1, 19 Nov. 1986 (Box Series III-3)
    - Folder #2, 19 Nov. 1986 (Box Series III-3)
  - The False Faces of the Iroquois (Draft)--Ms. (Box Series III-3)
    - Folder #1, [1986?] (Box Series III-3)
    - Folder #2, [1986?] (Box Series III-3)
    - Folder #3, [1986?] (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #4, [1986?] (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #5, [1986?] (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #6, [1986?] (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #7, [1986?] (Box Series III-4)
  - The False Faces of the Iroquois (Edited Ms.)--Ms. (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #1, [1987?] (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #2, [1987?] (Box Series III-4)
    - Folder #3, [1987?] (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #4, [1987?] (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #5, [1987?] (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #6, [1987?] (Box Series III-5)
  - The False Faces of the Iroquois--Notes (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #1, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #2, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #3, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-5)
    - Folder #4, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-6)
    - Folder #5, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-6)
    - Folder #6, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-6)
    - Folder #7, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-6)
    - Folder #8, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box Series III-6)
  - The False Faces of the Iroquois--Notes re Sapir correspondence, Jun. 1984 (Box Series III-6)
  - The False Faces of the Iroquois--Research, 1838, 1888-1987, n.d. (Box Series III-6)
  - "Fish Drives Among the Cornplanter Senecas"--Ms., 1942 (Box Series III-6)
    -See also Ser. I, Schultz, L.P.
  - Flies in the Water, Fish in the Air: A Personal Introduction to Fly Fishing by Jim Arnosky--Review, 17 May 1988 (Box Series III-6)
  - "Frank G. Speck's Anthropology"--Ms., 17 Feb. 1978 (Box Series III-6)
  - "Frank G. Speck's Anthropology"--Originals, 17 Feb. 1978 (Box Series III-6)
    prefer use of photocopies in "--Ms." file
  - "Frank G. Speck's Anthropology"--Research, n.d. (Box Series III-6)
    -See also Ser. IV, Hallowell, A. Irving, "Frank Gouldsmith Speck"
    -See also Ser. IV, Hartgen, Karen S., "Frank G. Speck"
    -See also Ser. IV, Keller, Judith A., "Frank Gouldsmith Speck"
  - "Fred Russell Eggan (1906-1991)"--Ms., [13 Jun. 1991] (Box Series III-7)
  - "Frederick Starr, Jesse Cornplanter and the Cornplanter Medal for Iroquois Research" (Box Series III-7)
  - "From Longhouse to Ranch-Type House: The Second Housing Revolution of the Seneca Nations"--Ms., 1965 (Box Series III-7)
    -See also Ser. VI, same title
  - "The Funeral of Tadodaho: Onondaga of Today"--Ms., 1968 (Box Series III-7)
  - "A Further Note on Iroquois Suicide"--Ms., 1986 (Box Series III-7)
  - Hale, Horatio Emmons, 1985, n.d. (Box Series III-7)
    -See also Ser. I, Canada. Province of British Columbia Archives
    -See also Ser. I, Canada. Public Archives of Canada
    -See also Ser. I, Cole, Douglas
    -See also Ser. I, Dictionary of Canadian Biography
    -See also Ser. I, Hartley, Erma Hale
    -See also Ser. I, Huron County Public Library
    -See also Ser. I, Library-Anthropology Resource Group
    -See also Ser. I, McFeat, Thomas
    -See also Ser. I, Metropolitan Toronto Library Board
    -See also Ser. I, Olde, Evelyn
    -See also Ser. I, Royal Ontario Museum
    -See also Ser. I, Toronto Public Archives
    -See also Ser. I, University of Rochester
    -See also Ser. I, University of Western Ontario
    -See also Ser. I, Woodbury, Nathalie
    -See also Ser. IV, Tooker, Elisabeth, "The Hale-Morgan Correspondence"
  - Hear Me, My Chiefs by Herbert Ravenel Sass--Review, [11 Dec. 1940] (Box Series III-7)
  - "An Herbarium From the Allegany Senecas", 1939 (Box Series III-7)
    -See also Ser. I, Mayer, Karl Stephen
    -See also Ser. I, Stefansson, Vilhjalmur
  - "Herbs and Herbalists among the Iroquois Indians"--Ms., 1940 (Box Series III-7)
  - "History and Purposes of the Conference on Iroquois Research"--Ms., 1965 (Box Series III-7)
  - A History of Medicine. Vol. I: Primitive and Archaic Medicine by Henry E. Sigerist--Review, [1951] (Box Series III-7)
  - "Howard Sky, 1900-1971: Cayuga Faith-Keeper, Gentleman, and Interpreter of Iroquois Culture"--Ms. (Box Series III-7)
    -See also Ser. VI, Sky, Howard, 1956, n.d.
  - "I Plant a Tree of Light in the Town of Colonie: Or an Indian Giver in the 1960's"--Commencement address at Colonie Central High School, 26 Jun. 1961 (Box Series III-7)
  - "The Image of the Iroquois: Fiend or Friend"--Ms. (first draft), [1964] (Box Series III-7)
  - "The Image of the Iroquois: Fiend or Friend"--Ms. (revised), 1964 (Box Series III-7)
  - "In Memoriam: Harry Watt and Avery Jimerson"--Ms., 18 Jun. 1986 (Box Series III-7)
  - Indian Arts in North America by George C. Vaillant--Review, [1939] (Box Series III-7)
  - "The Indian Arts Project on the Tonawanda Reservation"--Ms., 1935 (Box Series III-7)
    -See also Ser. VI, Ground, H. #1, [1935]
  - Indian Experiences by DeCost Smith--Review, [2 May 1943] (Box Series III-7)
  - "The Indian Show Goes Educational"--Ms., 1934 (Box Series III-7)
  - "Indian Treaty Protocol: The Crucible of Indian-White Relations"--Ms., 24 Feb. 1979 (Box Series III-7)
  - "Indians, Anthropologists, and the Museum"--Ms., 23 Nov. 1972 (Box Series III-7)
  - "Indians in the Adirondacks"--Lecture, 21 Jul. 1975 (Box Series III-7)
  - "Indians in the Adirondacks"--Original, 21 Jul. 1975 (Box Series III-7)
    prefer use of photocopy in "--Lecture" file
  - Indians of the United States: Four Centuries of Their History and Culture by Clark Wissler--Review, 1941 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Installing a Cayuga Chief in 1945"--Ms., 1946 (Box Series III-8)
  - "An Interpretation of Agriculture in the Northeast" (Box Series III-8)
  - "Interview With Mildred Garlow"--Ms., 10 Aug. 1959 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Iroquoian Culture History: A General Evaluation"--Ms., 1961 (Box Series III-8)
  - "The Iroquois Confederacy in the Twentieth Century: A Case Study of the Theory of Lewis H. Morgan in "Ancient Society""--Distribution list, 1965 (Box Series III-8)
  - The Iroquois Eagle Dance: An Offshoot of the Calumet Dance, 1953-1954, 1991 (Box Series III-8)
    -See also Ser. I, Carpenter, Edmund S., 1953
    -See also Ser. I, Dockstader, Frederick, J.
    -See also Ser. I, Gansworth, Howard
    -See also Ser. I, Haekel, Josef
    -See also Ser. I, Holt, Josephine
    -See also Ser. I, Jennings, Jesse D.
    -See also Ser. I, Kurath, Gertrude
    -See also Ser. I, McKennan, Robert A.
    -See also Ser. I, Randle, Martha Huot
    -See also Ser. I, Witthoft, John
  - "The Iroquois in History"--Ms., 1967, n.d. (Box Series III-8)
  - "Iroquois Political History: An Anthropological View"--Ms., [1984] (Box Series III-8)
    -See also Ser. IIa, The "Imperial" Iroquois--Conference on Early American History
  - "Iroquois Studies at the Mid-Century", 1951 (Box Series III-8)
    -See also Ser. I, Bell, Robert E.
    -See also Ser. I, Drummond, Richard
    -See also Ser. I, Whitehill, Walter Muir
  - "Iroquois Suicide: A Study in the Stability of a Culture Pattern", 1935 (Box Series III-8)
    -See also Ser. I, Barbeau, C. Marius (1939)
    -See also Ser. I, Congdon, Charles E. (1941)
    -See also Ser. I, Deardorff, Merle H. (1941)
    -See also Ser. I, Gordon, Robert B. (1940)
    -See also Ser. I, Kluckhohn, Clyde (1941)
    -See also Ser. I, Wayne, H.A. (1939)
  - The Iroquois: The People of the Longhouse, 1960 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Iroquois Use of Plants as Medicines"--Ms., [1954] (Box Series III-8)
  - "J.-F. Lafitau (1681-1746), Precursor of Scientific Anthropology"--Notes & distribution list, [1969] (Box Series III-8)
  - "John C. Ewers and the Great Tradition of Artists and Ethnologists of the West"--Ms., 1980 (Box Series III-8)
  - "John Reed Swanton (1873-1958)"--Obituary, 1959 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Johnson Jimerson (1918-1984)"--Ms., 23 Oct. 1984 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Keeping the Promise: Return of the Wampums to the Six Nations Iroquois Confederacy, Grand River"--Ms., 8 May 1988 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Lafitau, Joseph-François" (Dictionary of Canadian Biography), 1974 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Lafitau, Joseph-François" (Library-Anthropology Resource Group)--Ms., 7 Jul. 1988 (Box Series III-8)
  - "Leadership in the Northeastern Woodlands of North America"--Ms. and notes, [1985] (Box Series III-8)
  - "The League of the Five Nations: An Early American Indian Democracy"--Notes, 1942 (Box Series III-8)
    -See also Ser. I, Smithsonian Institution, 1942
  - League of the Iroquois: Its History, Politics and Ritual (Box Series III-8)
    - Folder #1, Ms., 17 Jul. 1974 (Box Series III-8)
    - Folder #2, Ms., n.d. (Box Series III-9)
    - Folder #3, Originals, 17 Jul. 1974 (Box Series III-9)
  - Letters of Francis Parkman. Wilbur R. Jacobs, Ed.--Review, 1961 (Box Series III-9)
  - "Long Term Trends of Change Among the Iroquois"--Ms., 1957 (Box Series III-9)
  - "Lore of the Longhouse"--Lecture, 30 Apr. 1975 (Box Series III-9)
  - Lore of the Longhouse: Deganawidah's League for Peace--Ms., 27 Aug. 1970 (Box Series III-9)
  - Lore of the Longhouse: Deganawidah's League for Peace--Originals, 27 Aug. 1970 (Box Series III-9)
  - "The Lore of the Longhouse: Deganawi:'dah's Message"--Ms., 1978 (Box Series III-9)
  - "Maori Acculturation"--Ms., [1978] (Box Series III-9)
  - "Masked Medicine Societies of the Iroquois", [1940] (Box Series III-9)
    -See also Ser. III, The False Faces of the Iroquois--Notes
  - "Merwick on Possessing Albany"--Ms., n.d. (Box Series III-9)
  - "Mohawk" (Box Series III-9)
    - Folder #1, Ms. (edited), 1973 (Box Series III-9)
    - Folder #2, Ms. (first draft), 1973 (Box Series III-9)
    - Folder #3, Originals (first draft), 1973 (Box Series III-9)
    - Folder #4, Ms. (revised), 1974-1975 (Box Series III-10)
    - Folder #5, Ms. (Tooker draft), [1977] (Box Series III-10)
  - Mohawk Baronet by James Thomas Flexner--Review, [1959] (Box Series III-10)
  - "More Books About Indians"--Review, [2 Jun. 1940] (Box Series III-10)
  - "Morgan's Legacy to Iroquois Studies and to American Ethnology"--Ms., [1981]; 2 folders (Box Series III-10)
    -See also Ser. IIa, "Kin and Communities: The Peopling of America:--Smithsonian Symposium
  - "A Native American Political System: The League of the Iroquois"--Lecture, 17 Mar. 1959 (Box Series III-10)
  - "A New Charter for Indian Affairs in New York State"--Ms., [1971] (Box Series III-10)
  - New Voices From the Iroquois Longhouse: An Anthology of Contemporary Iroquois Writing by Joseph Bruchac--Review, [1989] (Box Series III-10)
  - "The New York State Wampum Collection: The Case for the Integrity of Cultural Treasures" (version I)--Ms. (Box Series III-10)
    - Folder #1, 1970 (Box Series III-10)
    - Folder #2, 1970 (Box Series III-10)
  - "The New York State Wampum Collection: The Case for the Integrity of Cultural Treasures" (version II)--Ms., 30 Nov. 1970 (Box Series III-10)
  - "The New York State Wampum Collection: The Case for the Integrity of Cultural Treasures" (version III)--Ms., 1970 (Box Series III-10)
  - "Northern Iroquoian Culture Patterns"--Ms., 1974 (Box Series III-10)
  - The Ordeal of the Longhouse: The Peoples of the Iroquois League in the Era of European Colonization by Daniel K. Richter--Review (Box Series III-10)
  - "Outdoor Wisdom." [Review of] The Boy Campers by William Hillcourt, [1931] (Box Series III-10)
  - Parker on the Iroquois, 1968-1972, 1982-1983, n.d. (Box Series III-10)
    -See also Ser. VI, Parker on the Iroquois (1945, n.d.)
  - "The Peace of 1645 at Three Rivers, Quebec: An Ethnological Perspective"--Ms., n.d. (Box Series III-10)
  - "Pennsylvania's Remaining Indian Settlement"--Ms., [1945] (Box Series III-10)
  - "The People of the Longhouse"--Outline, 1960 (Box Series III-10)
  - [Pickering Treaty]--Ms., n.d.; 5 folders (Box Series III-11)
  - "Place Names and Related Activities of the Cornplanter Senecas", [19--] (Box Series III-11)
    -See also Ser. I, Adney, E. Tappan
    -See also Ser. I, Robinson, Percy
  - "Problems of Ethnological Research in North American Museums"--Ms., [1964?] (Box Series III-11)
  - "A Proposal for a Committee on the Anthropology of Eastern North America"--Ms., 1953 (Box Series III-11)
  - "Recording Iroquois Music; Translating the Legend of Deganawidah's League of Five Nations"--Ms., 1941 (Box Series III-11)
  - "Report on the Status of Indian Self-Government in Three Tribal Cultures: Taos, Klamath, and Blackfeet" (Box Series III-11)
    -See Ser. III, "Report on the Status of Tribal Government in Three Tribal Cultures..."
  - "Report on the Status of Tribal Government in Three Tribal Cultures: Taos, Klamath, and Blackfeet"--Ms., 1950 (Box Series III-11)
  - "The Requickening Address of the Iroquois Condolence Council" by J.N.B. Hewitt. W.N.F., editor (Box Series III-11)
    -See Ser. I, Becker, Howard
    -See Ser. I, Knowles, Francis H.S.
    -See Ser. I, Royal Canadian Institute
    -See Ser. I, Harrington, M.R.
  - "Return of the Wampums to the Six Nations Iroquois Confederacy on Grand River" (Box Series III-11)
    -See Ser. III, "Keeping the Promise: Return of the Wampums to the Six Nations Iroquois Confederacy, Grand River"
  - "Return to the Longhouse"--Ms., 1970 (Box Series III-11)
    -See also Ser. VI, Fenton, John William and Jones Snow (1933)
  - "Return to the Longhouse"--Originals, 1970 (Box Series III-11)
  - "Sapir as Museologist and Research Director, 1910-1925"--Ms., 3 Dec. 1984 (Box Series III-11)